Frank G. Speck Papers 1903-1950 Mss.Ms.Coll.126
American Philosophical Society
- Subcollection I. Frank G. Speck Papers, 1897-1950; 10 linear feet
  - Series I. Research Material, 1903-1950; 8.25 linear feet
    - IV. Southeast
      - E. Catawba
        - Correspondence with other informants, 1917-1944; IV(18E2); 17 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Catawba correspondence. Leola Blue to Speck, concerning pottery specimens, reservation activities: Oct. 21, 1917, A.L.S., 2p.; Dec. 27, 1917, A.L.S., 2p.; Oct. 12, 1919, A.L.S., 3p.; Oct. 27, 1919, A.L.S., 4p.; Nov. 1, 1919, A.L.S., 3p.; Dec. 5, 1919, A.L.S., 3p.; Dec. 13, 1919, A.L.S.,2p. Mrs. Nettle O. Harris, Dec. 2, 1921, A.L.S., 3p. and 1 scrap, concerning specimens sent. Mrs. R. L. Harris, Nov. 17, 1930, A.L.S., 1p., concerning Catawba politics interfering with distribution of church Christmas gifts. Chief [Sam] Blue, March 17, 1944, A.L.S., 3p. Cherokee correspondence: Climbing Bear to Speck, July 30, 1928, A.L.S., 2p., concerning masks and dances (Swayney, N.C.). Will West Long, Aug. 22, 1929, A.L.S., 3p., concerning museum specimens and explanation of use; Sept. 10?, 1929, A.L.S., 2p., concerning masks and dances; Nov. 20, 1929, A.L.S., 4p., concerning sticks, baskets, masks of corn husks, dances; Dec. 1, 1929, A.L.S., 3p., concerning specimens and murder of his step-father at Thanksgiving party; Dec. 27, 1929, A.L.S., 5p., concerning specimens.
          F&S 520
        - Catawba food resources, 1942; IV(18E3); 7 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Includes 1p. list of foods gathered by Indians; 2p, notes on food; 1p. chart of animals used for food; 4p. charts of animals, birds, fish utilized in Catawba economy
          F&S 514
        - [no entry], IV(18E4) (Box 12)
        - [no entry], IV(18E5) (Box 12)
        - Racial Status, 1938; IV(18E6); 3 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          An explanatory note on Catawbas as a group, discussing their fear of being classed as Negroes in South Carolina. MS. notes added to reprint, John Walker McCain, Jr. (1934).
          F&S 517
        - Catawba field notebooks, miscellaneous, 1937-1946; IV(19E7); 4 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Notebooks dated 1914, 1921, 1922, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1931, 1937. Includes texts (both folkloristic and ethnographic), vocabulary, ethnologic notes, conjugations, grammatical notes, linguistic notes. Some Cherokee, Houma, Pamunkey materials in the 1937 books
          F&S513
        - Catawba bibliography, 1942; IV(18E8); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          "For Hunting MS., 1942."
          F&S 511
        - "The Catawba - A Small Nation Deflated", IV(18E9); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Notes and reflections on the Catawba; perhaps a lecture.
          F&S 518
        - Miscellaneous Notes, 1925-1946; IV(18E10); 37 items (Box 12)
          Includes 25p. reading notes and linguistic notes; 25 cards of reading notes on Catawba, Cheraw, Cherokee; 1p. on house building; 5p. reading notes and sketch; 1p. note on use of gourds (Feb. 1929); 1p. notes on primitive law; 1p. note on bibliography; 2p, reading notes; 7p. miscellaneous; 4p. text and grammatical notes. Correspondence to Speck: John R. Swanton, Oct. 8, 1931, T.L.S., 2p., concerning tribe-band locations and names for Montagnais-Naskapi and queries concerning Siouian predecessors of Cherokee and Yuchi as the Hopewell. (1p. note of Speck on reverse); Oct. 16, 1931, T.L.S., 2p. concerning Yuchi, Catawba Ilames and Spanish sources; May 11, 1928, T.L.S., Zp., concerning Speck collecting Catawba texts; April 2, 1931, T.L.S., 1p., concerning Catawba and problems of name derivation; April 22, 1931, T.L.S., 1p., concerning Sioux predecessors and Cherokee, their divisions; June 14, 1933, T.L.S., 2p., concerning Yuchi names, Cherokee and other Southeast tribes; Jan. 15, 1925, T.L.S., 2p. Catawba and Wataree the same. Mary R. Haas, Oct. 28, 1940, T.L.S., 4p., concerning comparisons of Catawba with Creek, Tutelo with Cherokee. Jeffrey L. Coe, May 10, 1938, T.L.S., 1p., concerning search for Siouan sites for archaeological study in Southeast. Douglas L. Rights, Feb. 13, 1933, T.L.S., 1p.; April 20, 1933, T.L.S., 2p.; Sept. 14, 1938, T.L.S., 1p., concerning publication prospects for Speck's Catawba ethnology volume. A. R. Newsome (North Carolina Historical Commission), March 28, 1933, T.L.S., 1p., rejects Speck's Catawba manuscript. Erminie W. Voegelin, Feb. 16, 1939, A.L.S., 2p., concerning Shawnee, Yuchi, Catawba, and Tutelo ethnologic comparisons. Carl Voegelin, n.d. (ca. Feb. 1939), A.L.S., 2p., with 8p. notes of E. W. Voegelin on role of celestial bodies (Shawnee); re Shawnee. Raymond --- (Southwest Museum, Los Angeles), Oct. 23, 1946, T.L.S., 1p., concerning Iroquois affairs; Speck's Catawba reprint (1946). Claude Schaeffer, n.d., A.L.S., 1p., concerning early map of Catawba country. W. N. Fenton, n.d., 1p. fragment, concerning distribution of Calumet dance. Leonard Broom, Nov. 1, 1938, A.L.S., 1p., concerning Cherokee and Catawba writings. Images note: 2 sketches of Catawba dwellings.
          F&S 516
        - Travel and Expedition, IV(18E11); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Extract from Catawba ethnography manuscript on means of travel.
          F&S 522
        - Division of time, n.d.; IV(18E12); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Seasons, months, etc.; explanation of units and names.
          F&S 512
        - [no entry], IV(18E13) (Box 12)
        - Language and texts, 1922-1939; IV(18E14); 24 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          2p. notes on two words; 4p. typed D., c.c., 4 Catawba tales from Sam Blue; 5p. phonetic text (with interlinear translation and notes); ca. 60 cards and slips-paradigms, linguistic notes; T.D., 1p., text in English; 16p. of comparative vocabulary (215 English words with equivalents in 10 Siouan languages); 2p. grammatical forms; 7p. text and Ip, note. Correspondence: John R. Swanton to Speck, Feb. 18, 1922, T.L.S., 1p., concerning a Catawba grammar. Henry C. Davis, Jan. 9, 1936, T.L.S., 1p., concerning Catawba numerals and words from 1854 MS. of Oscar M. Lieber, Charter, S.C. Albert Keiser, Sept. 10, 1937, T.L.S., 1p., concerning origin of Catawba name and Catawba migration. Morris Swadesh, Aug. 11, 1937, A.L.S., 5p., concerning Catawba vowels and phonetics and his Catawba field work; Sept. 25, 1937, T.L.S., 2p., concerning Catawba phonemes; n.d., A.L.S. 2p., with 1p. text with note from Swadesh on phonetics.
          F&S 548
        - Catawba tribal history, n.d.; IV(18E15); 8 items; Cadwalader, John (Box 12)
          12p. historical sketch by John Cadwalader, a student at the University of Pennsylvania, and 3p. of notes from eighteenth-century sources.
          F&S 527
        - General ethnological notes, 1943-1944; IV(18E16); 18 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Includes 24p. Typed D., "Catawba ethnology"; 15p. of copies of same; 8p. Typed c.c., Copy of "Division of time" [see 18:4E12]; 5p. Typed D., English text; 18p. "An Addendum to Catawba Indian herbals & curative practices, March 26, 1943:"
          F&S 515
        - Genealogies, 1942; IV(18E17); 5 items; Speck, Florence I. (Box 12)
          Genealogies of twentieth-century Catawba informants, giving names, birth dates and birthplace, children, locations of tribes. 2p. reading notes on location of tribes.
          F&S 510
        - Social Organizations, 1937; IV(18E18); 2 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          3p. charts of kinship terms; 1p. note and 17p. of cards containing Catawba kinship terms, phonetic spelling. Letters to Speck from A. I. Hallowell, June 25, 1937, A.L.S., 2p., concerning published references on Southeastern kinship data; n.d., A.L.S., 3p., concerning Speck and Schaeffer (1942).
          F&S 519
        - Catawba field notebook: vocabulary, texts and songs, IV(18E19); 9 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 12)
          Catawba field notebooks: vocabulary, texts, and songs
          F&S 547
      - F.Virginia (Powhatan Algonkians)
        - 2. Pamunkey
          - a. Contemporary technology, n.d.; IV(21F2a); 5 items (arrowhead); Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Miscellaneous notes on material culture; projectile point.
            F&S 3039
          - b. Hunting and fishing, 1940-1945; IV(21F2b); 29 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Map of hunting stands; 6p., c.c., "Notes on Pamunkey Deer Drive, 1938-1939"; 2p. listing of costume ornaments; 42p. on game practices; notebook of communal game drive (12p); 2p. on cage traps and fish bait; 12p. charts on animals and fish used; 1p. list of functions of animals; 1p. explanation of division of game; 7p. notes and sketch of hunting club; 3p. "Accessories Co Hunting, " listing clubs, poles, paddles, stretchers. Correspondence: Claude E. Schaeffer to Speck, Sept. 17, 1945 and Nov. 20, 1943, 2 postal cards, concerning game drives; E. P. Bradby to Speck, June 2, 1945, A.L.S., 1p., concerning hunting clubs and Indian (Pamunkey) birth certificates. Image note: 14 ink sketches of 2p. Pamunkey pictographic tablet, both drawing and explanation; sketch of hunting club.
            F&S 3045
          - c. Emergency foods, n.d.; IV(21F2c); 2 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            Charts of plants and other items considered edible (i.e., not regular diet).
            F&S 3041
          - d. "Virginia Indians Past and Present" newspaper article, IV(21F2d); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            Printed, Richmond, Va., Times Dispatch, 1940.
            F&S 3054
          - e. "Pamunkey Town" in 1759, n.d.; IV(21F2e); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            An account based on Andrew Burnaby, Travels (1760).
            F&S 3051
          - f. Miscellaneous notes, 1920-1922; IV(21F2f); 8 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            4p. miscellaneous notes; letter of Chief Cook to Speck, June 30, 1922, A.L.S., 3p., concerning cane for museum specimen. Images note: 2 ink sketches, 3p. description and sketch of Pamunkey refuse pit; 1p. sketch of trap; 3 newspaper clipping photographs of groups of Pamunkey men.
            F&S 3048
          - g. Pamunkey folklore and language, 1940; IV(21F2g); 20 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            9p. English folklore (tales and sayings); Ilp. miscellaneous folklore; 1p. sketch of metal bracelet for curing rheumatism (Nov., 1939); 5p. folklore and English language idioms collected by R. R. Solenberger; 1p. Pamunkey words ("of doubtful authenticity, FGS") taken from a Tuscarora who had married a Pamunkey (Peter Cusick); 4p. folklore superstitions (sic) obtained by Jack Kremens from Paul and Nancy Miles.
            F&S 3043
          - h. "Pamunkey Pottery", 1941; IV(21F2h); 1 item; Stern, Theodore (Box 14)
            Manuscript in 4 parts with a 5p. Appendix (142p. -t 5p.); also 4p., c.c., a bibliography of southeastern pottery; 2p., c.c., discussion of aboriginal pottery technique, possibly by Speck.
            F&S 3057
          - i. Plants and agriculture, 1940; IV(21F2i); 10 items; Kremens, Jack (Box 14)
            8p. typed list of shrubs, flowers, and their use; 4p. list of trees and uses; 2p. list of farm produce and use. 6p. notes of Frank G. Speck (?) on plants and their use and a letter of William N. Fenton to Speck, Feb. 26, 1940, T.L.S., 1p., concerning plant identification.
            F&S 3024
          - j. Pamunkey, Celestial and Meteorological Phenomena, 1940; IV(21F2j); 3 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            Copied from field notes.
            F&S 3038
          - k. Pamunkey Mensuration, n.d.; IV(21F2k); 3 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            Units of measure; measurement of time; technique of determining right angle.
            F&S 3047
          - l. Pamunkey Birds, n.d.; IV(21F2l); 4 items; Kremens, Jack (Box 14)
            7p. list of 76 English bird names used by the Pamunkey, together with their generic and common names and the uses made of these birds. 4p. miscellaneous.
            F&S 3023
          - m. Pamunkey reptiles, 1940; IV(21F2m); 2 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            2p. description of turtle-catching techniques; 1p. list of snakes.
            F&S 3049
          - n. Pamunkey fish, amphibians, and reptiles, 1939; IV(21F2n); 4 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            List of fish, amphibians, crustacea, reptiles, their uses (6p. typed); 4p. miscellaneous.
            F&S 3042
          - o. Pamunkey medicines and poisons, 1940; IV(21F2o); 13 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            1 notebook of 28p. concerning Pamunkey folklore and medicines; Mattaponi folklore and hunting; Rappahannock folklore and medicines; Chickahominy folklore. 1p. conceming Rappahannock lovelore; 1p. on medicines; 8p. cards and scraps, miscellany on medicines and 1p. by R. Solenberger on Pamunkey medicine.
            F&S 3046
          - p. Pamunkey foods, 1939-1940; IV(21F2p); 19 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            2p. concerning fungus; 9p. concerning food habits; 2p. on huntings; 1p. on Croatan foods; 2p. on remedies; 1p. note on cookery, 1940; 7p., c.c., cooking notes, Pamunkey, 1939; 2p., c.c. Mattaponi cooking; 2p., c.c., Chickahominy cooking; 2p. reading notes. 2p. notes on Indian bread, 1939, by Howard G. Henry.
            F&S 3044
          - q. [no entry], IV(21F2q) (Box 14)
          - r. Social Organization, 1940; IV(21F2r); 6 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            1p., Pamunkey band composition; 1p. reading notes; 5p. miscellaneous notes; Waiter Bradby to Speck, Nov. 19, 1940, A.L.S., lp., concerning sending delegation of Virginia Indians to Washington, D.C., seeking Indian status.
            F&S 3050
          - s. Correspondence with informants, 1921-1940; IV(21F2s); 7 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 14)
            From Pamunkey Indians: Paul L. Miles to Speck, Jan. 12, 1922, A.L.S., 2p., and April 9, 1940, A.L.S., 1p., concerning gourd seeds (1p. sketch of newt on back of latter) Miles to Speck, Nov. 27, 1921, A.L.S., 2p. (incomplete, may not be Miles), concerning organizing Virginia Indians; Dec. 16, 192?, A.L.S., 2p., on same subject. Chief O. W. Adkins, Mar. 21, 1921, A.L.S., 3p., friendly letter. From whites: R. B. Van Oot (Virginia government official), Dec. 14, 1931, T.L.S., 1p., denying teaching job to ex-Chief Miles; W. F. Jones, Fredericksburg, Va., Mar. 1, 1940, T.L.S., 1p., concerning per cent of Indian blood in Bradby family.
            F&S 3040
          - t. Animals, 1940; IV(21F2t); 4 items; Kremens, Jack (Box 14)
            4p. typed list of 21 animals and their uses; also Kremens to Speck, July 19, 1940, A.L.S., 1p., transmitting the list and describing identifications as tentative. 2p. miscellaneous notes.
            F&S 3022
          - u. Games and amusements, 1941; IV(21F2u); 1 item; Rowell, Mary (Box 14)
            A report by a student of Speck, used in a publication?
            F&S 3025
        - 1. General and Historical
          - a. Gourds in early contact days, n.d.; IV(20F1a); 5 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Reading notes taken from 1855 edition of Robert Beverley's History of Virginia.
            F&S 3034
          - b. Bow and arrow in early contact days, IV(20F1b); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Reading notes on Virginia Indians.
            F&S 3028
          - c. [no entry], IV(20F1c) (Box 13)
          - d. Miscellaneous notes, 1940-1947; IV(20F1d); 23 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            3p. of reading notes; 1p. sketch of nets; 2p. notes; 8p. series of letters, 1940, pertaining to Social Work Conference paper on Virginia Indians; 3p. miscellaneous notes; T.D., c.c., 2p., concerning Virginia Indians and their villages. Correspondence includes: Charles E. Gilliam to Speck, Sept. 22, 1947, T.L.S., 1p., concerning irregularity of design in Powhatan pottery; M. D. Hard. Apr. 5, 1940, T.L.S., 1p., concerning racial purity as goal for Virginia Indians; Chief J. H. Johnson (Ga-Yen-Twa-ga, or Complanter), May 1, 1940, A.L.S., 2p., concerning Speck's speech on Virginia Indians; George G. Heye, Apr. 18, 1940, T.I, .S., 2p., lists Chickahominy, Pamunkey, Rappahanock specimens received; Mrs. J. R. Darden, July 11, 1940, T.L.S., 1p., seeks authoritative data on Indian art, music, and literature; Dr. Belie Boone Beard, Dec. 1, 1940, A.L.S., 5p., concerning schools for Virginia Indians; Speck to G. A. Brakeley (University of Pennsylvania), May 2, 1939, concerning grant for ethno-ecologic study of tidewater area.
            F&S 3036
          - e. Racial status of Virginia Indians, IV(20F1e) (Box 13)
            Item not located as of 4/10/96, not on microfilm #1429 or in Freeman guide
          - f. Field notebooks, representing several communities, n.d.; IV(20F1f); 6 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Ethnologic notes; information separated by group. Includes a few notes on Cherokee. Images note: 1 ink sketch of rock.
            F&S 3033
          - g. Draft classification of Virginia Indians, 1940-1946; IV(20F1g); 82 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Correspondence (42 letters) and copies of various documents relating to efforts of Frank G. Speck, James R. Coates, and others to overcome practice of Virginia local draft boards to classify Virginia Indians as Negroes for Selective Service. Also Charles D. Humberd, M.D., "Pickett Nelson, " 5p. T.D., copy, and Ella N. Wade (of College of Physicians and Surgeons), Oct. 9, 1941, T.L.S., 1p., transmitting same: concerns a giant Rappahannock of late nineteenth century. 25p. of typed letters of U.S. Senators on Indian Committee, 1944-1945, and c.c.'s of letters to same by Speck and James R. Coates, opposing Indian Bills before the Senate. Charles E. Gilliam to Speck, May 21, 1945, T.L.S., 1p., concerning Gilliam's articles on ethnobotany of Virginia Algonkians.
            F&S 3032
          - h. Powhatan Algonkian birds, etc., in colonial times, 1946; IV(20F1h); 3 items; Gilliam, Charles Edgar (Box 13)
            2p., c.c., memo on bird names (with note to Speck and to Father Geary); 3p., c.c., to Wm. B. McIlwaine, same subject; 3p., May 2, 1946, same subject.
            F&S 3061
          - i. Correspondence, 1943-1947; IV(20F1i); 12 items; Gilliam, Charles Edgar (Box 13)
            Gilliam, a Petersburg, Va., attorney and amateur etymologist and ethnologist. June 10, 1943, T.L.S., 1p., concerning names of Pocahontas, Oppusioquionuske; July 24, 1943, T.L.S., 3p., legal advice re Oliver Fortune case; July 12, 1943, T.L.S., 1p. Indian names in seventeenth century; July 19, 1943, T.L.S., 1p., colonists hostile propaganda on Indians; July 21, 1943, T.L.S., 1p., Indian-White relations, seventeenth century; July 27, 1943, T.L.S., 4p., re Powhatan marital and sex customs; June 16, 1943, T.L.S., 2p., concerning gourds; June 19, 1943, T.D. c.c., 6p., concerning the Appomatoc, from historic sources; Aug. 17, 1943, T.L.S., 2p., conceming Fortune case and gourds; Sept. 15, 1943, T.L.S., 1p., June 27, 1944, T.L.S., 1p., both re Negro-White relations; Sept. 22, 1944, T.L.S., 2p., re Seminoles and hurricanes; Sept. 27, 1944, T.L.S., 2p.; May 16, 1946, T.L.S., 2p., with transcript of Oct. 29, 1855 land transfer with Gilliam's comments; Oct. 38, 1946, T.L., c.c., 2p., to Miss Anniel re Powhatan place name; Nov. 5, 1946, T.L.S., 1p. and 4p. c.c. on bird name meanings; Nov. 7, 1946, T.L.S., 6p., re bird names; Dec. 16, 1946, T.L.S., 2p., re bird names and etymology; May 19, 1946, postal card, re land and place names; Jan. 11, 1947, 3p. c.c., concerning Virginia Indian arrowheads; Jan. 22, 1947, T.L.S., 1p. and 3p. memo (c.c.) for Father Geary, concerning bird names. April 28, 1944, T.L.S., 1p., re Appomattac villages and incidents in colonial Virginia.
            F&S 3021
          - j. Virginia Indian population in 1668, 1943; IV(20F1j); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Comments on figures obtained from regulation requiring certain numbers of wolves be killed by various Indian groups.
            F&S 3055
        - 3. Rappahanock
          - a. Contemporary technology, n.d.; IV(20F3a); 1 item; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Image note: 1 ink sketch of bag string (bag sling).
            F&S 3052
          - b. Field notes, 1940; IV(20F3b); 3 items; Sollenberger, R. (Box 13)
            1p. on English idioms of the Rappahannock; 5p. on baskets, fire drill, medicinals and a Penobscot Dance used by the Rappahannocks.
            F&S 3027
          - c. Miscellaneous notes, 1921-1946; IV(20F3c); 6 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            1p. card and 4p. notes taken in field. 1p. poem, "Memorial flowers, " c.c., by Robert Clark, a Rappahannock, Dec. 2, 1923. Let ters of Otho S. Nelson, May 17, 1940, A.L.S. 3p., and Aug. 23, 1940, A.L.S., 2p., explaining that it is other Virginia Indians who are doubtful of Speck. Letter of John M. Cooper to Speck, Oct. 28, 1948, T.L.S., 1p., concerning distribution of Rappahannock cage fall trap, its distribution in North and South America.
            F&S 3053
          - d. "Rappahanock Talking Dances", 1942; IV(20F3d); 1 item; Speck, Frank G., Royal B. Hassrick, and Edmund S. Carpenter (Box 13)
            Report on graduate student field trip, 1942. Description and use of traps and other hunting devices. Illustrations not included.
            F&S 3056
        - 4. Mattaponi (Adamstown)
          - a. miscellaneous notes, n.d.; IV(20F4); 6 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            7p. of miscellaneous materials on traditions and customs; 1 postal card of Speck to Florence I. Speck, concerning specimens and his field work among Mattaponi.
            F&S 3035
        - 5. Chickahominy
          - a. Incorporation as chartered tribe, 1939-1940; IV(20F5a); 6 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            Includes 3p. c.c. certification of incorporation; 1p. note, submitted by Speck, 1939, urging Indian status for Chickahominy. Letters to Chief E. P. Bradby to Speck: Feb. 9, 1940, T.L., 1p., re Treaty of 1613; Feb. 14, 1940, T.L., 1p. Bradby to F. Zimmerman (Bureau of Indian Affairs), Feb. 14, 1940, T.L., 1p., with 1p. typed list-of Tribal Roll of 52 members.
            F&S 3030
          - b. Miscellaneous notes, 1940-1945; IV(20F5b); 14 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)
            13p. of miscellaneous notes; 1p. re 1920 population of Virginia, comparing racial groups; 1p. history of Chickahominy; 1p. quote from E. P. Alldredge, The New Challenge of Home Missions (1927), Mimeo D.; 1p. telling of Baptist missionary ancestor of Bradby family. Correspondence, Frederic Douglas to Speck, April 4, 1940, T.L.S., 2p., concerning Virginia specimens sent to Denver Art Museum. C. E. Gilliam, April 17, 1945, typed postal card, 1p., concerning place names.
            F&S 3031
          - c. Correspondence with informants, 1924-1940; IV(20F5c); 14 items; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950 (Box 13)